okay so we have seen that we want
coherence and now the question is how do
we get it so how do we make caches
become coherent the first option is
don't do caching but this is really bad
for performance so we will not seriously
consider this but if there are no caches
then all of the axises go to memory and
then rights to that memory will be seen
by the reads to that memory and also the
order in which the memory receives the
rights is the order in which the rights
will be seen by all the court so the
system will be coherent the second
option is if all cores share the same
level one cache then the same argument
for coherence supplies the order of
Rights is the order seen by this level
one
cache and all of the accesses are going
to go to the same cache where they see
the same version of the block so the
system will be coherent but will still
have really bad performance better than
this but not by much now we can try to
do things like having private caches but
make them right through in that case the
memory is actually seeing all the rights
but the problem is that these caches are
still allowed to cache data that has
only been read forever so once we read a
value it doesn't matter that all the
other cores are writing their values
through to memory because the cache that
only reads will potentially see forever
the same stale value even after many
many rights have occurred and for a long
time so this is really not a way to get
coherence even with write through caches
private caches are not necessarily
coherent what we must do really is to
force reads made to one cash to see the
rights made in another so we cannot
allow cashes to Simply provide the same
value over and over once it's a cash hit
somehow once a right occurs in one cash
another cash needs to eventually start
returning that value to its local
processor so how do we do that one way
is for every right to be sent to all the
other caches that might potentially have
this block and they need to update their
value so pretty much I write to my cach
it's kind of like a write through cach
in that it continues past the cache but
now what really happens to it is not
only does it get written back to memory
it also get sent and seen by all the
other caches which now take that new
value if that that happens then when I
write other caches now have my new value
and then reads on those scores will
actually provide the same value this is
called Write update coherence because
wres update all of the other cach copies
the other approach for maintaining
coherence is for rights to
prevent other copies of the block from
having hits so after a write to one
cache all of the caches that had a copy
of this block need need to behave like
they're having a miss or they need to
behave like the block is not valid in
that cache so this is called Write
invalidate a write will invalidate all
the other copies note that these are
just the two general approaches we will
be looking at several right invalidate
coherence protocols and also we will be
considering a right update protocol so
this ensures really that reads see the
values produced by wres
so the coherence property two is
maintained by either this or this so we
need to pick one of these two approaches
to maintain coherence property two for
coherence property 3 we need to decide
what's the order of Rights and all the
cores need to see the same order one way
to enforce the same order of Rights
being seen by all the cores is that all
rights are broadcast on the shared bus
and then the order in which they appear
in this shared bus is the order that
should be seen by everybody coherence
done in this way is called snooping
because when rights are broadcast on the
bus everybody snoops those rights in
order to tell what order they occurred
on and also to update or invalidate
their values in the caches of course the
shared bus can now become a bottleneck
the other approach is that each block is
assigned an ordering point and different
ordering points can be used for
different blocks so that for each block
all axess Es are ordered by the same
entity but different blocks use
different entities so they don't have
contention this ordering point is called
directory when doing coherence so this
family of approaches is called a
directory based coherence and this
directory both serves as a ordering
point for a block and also figures out
who to update or invalidate when
multiple caches have a version of the
same block and a right occurs so among
these two approaches we can also pick
one and indeed all four possibilities
this and this this and this this and
this and this and that are all possible
so you can have WR update with snooping
WR update with directory WR inv validate
with snooping right inv validate with
directory